<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: RCP | Alex Proca]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexproca.ro/blog/categories/rcp/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexproca.ro/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-14T17:12:47+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexproca.ro/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Proca]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alex.proca@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Package an external library as an OSGi bundle]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexproca.ro/blog/2013/07/14/package-osgi-bundle/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-14T16:18:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexproca.ro/blog/2013/07/14/package-osgi-bundle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In an OSGi environment each plug-in has its own class-loader. If you use in your project an external dependency first thought is to embed the dependency in your bundle and that&rsquo;s all. This can lead to hard to debug ClassCastExceptions.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Scenario:</p>

<ol>
<li>You use an external library is called <strong>ZAB</strong></li>
<li>You make a library called <strong>FOO</strong> which embeds the <strong>ZAB</strong> library</li>
<li>Six months later somebody else create a second library <strong>BAR</strong> also embedding <strong>ZAB</strong></li>
<li>Then when you want to assembly the product and <strong>FOO</strong> provides some objects of class Zab.class to <strong>BAR</strong> library but the code will throw ClassCastException because the object of Zab.class was created in a different class-loader</li>
</ol>


<p>The correct approach is to package <strong>ZAB</strong> as a separate OSGi Bundle
<img src="/resources/trouble-osgi-library-inclusion.png" alt="Bundle external libraries" /></p>

<p>Fortunately maven bundle plug-in exists and packaging as OSGi bundle is piece of cake. Here you can see a simple configuration for packaging opencsv version 2.3 as an OSGi bundle.</p>

<p>If you want to try it out, install latest maven and copy the following code content in a pom.xml, then run <strong>mvn clean install</strong>. You will end up having a target folder and inside an OSGi bundle called <strong>dev.anproca.example.opencsv-2.3.0-SNAPSHOT.jar</strong></p>

<pre><code>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;project xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/maven-v4_0_0.xsd"&gt;
    &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;

    &lt;groupId&gt;dev.anproca.example&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;dev.anproca.example.opencsv&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;2.3.0-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;packaging&gt;bundle&lt;/packaging&gt;

    &lt;build&gt;
        &lt;plugins&gt;
            &lt;plugin&gt;
                &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.felix&lt;/groupId&gt;
                &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-bundle-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
                &lt;extensions&gt;true&lt;/extensions&gt;
                &lt;configuration&gt;
                    &lt;instructions&gt;
                        &lt;_exportcontents&gt;*&lt;/_exportcontents&gt;
                        &lt;Embed-Dependency&gt;*&lt;/Embed-Dependency&gt;
                        &lt;Import-Package&gt;&lt;/Import-Package&gt; 
                        &lt;Bundle-ClassPath&gt;{maven-dependencies}&lt;/Bundle-ClassPath&gt;
                        &lt;Embed-Transitive&gt;true&lt;/Embed-Transitive&gt;
                        &lt;Embed-Directory&gt;jars&lt;/Embed-Directory&gt;
                        &lt;Bundle-SymbolicName&gt;${project.artifactId}&lt;/Bundle-SymbolicName&gt;
                        &lt;_failok&gt;true&lt;/_failok&gt;
                        &lt;_nouses&gt;true&lt;/_nouses&gt;
                    &lt;/instructions&gt;
                &lt;/configuration&gt;
            &lt;/plugin&gt;
        &lt;/plugins&gt;
    &lt;/build&gt;

    &lt;dependencies&gt;
        &lt;dependency&gt;
            &lt;groupId&gt;net.sf.opencsv&lt;/groupId&gt;
            &lt;artifactId&gt;opencsv&lt;/artifactId&gt;
            &lt;version&gt;2.3&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;/dependency&gt;            
    &lt;/dependencies&gt;

&lt;/project&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>For more advanced configurations please visit <a href="http://felix.apache.org/site/apache-felix-maven-bundle-plugin-bnd.html" title="Maven Bundle Plugin">maven bundle plug-in website</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So you want RCP]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexproca.ro/blog/2013/07/14/begin-rcp-app/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-14T13:38:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexproca.ro/blog/2013/07/14/begin-rcp-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Fact</h1>

<p>RCP developing in serious projects can quickly became a nightmare if you do not use the appropriate tools.</p>

<h1>Developer Desires</h1>

<ul>
<li>to have a good IDE</li>
<li>to automate build and tests</li>
<li>to automate packaging of external dependencies</li>
<li>to automate deliver of further updates</li>
<li>to automate build of a product</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<h2>IDE</h2>

<p>In this post I will talk about eclipse as both platform and IDE. Yes you can use <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/documentation/usingIDEAforEclipse.html" title="RCP with intelij">intelij as IDE if you want</a> but it&rsquo;s kind of sacrilege.</p>

<p>When i write this post <a href="http://eclipse.org/kepler/" title="Eclipse Kepler">eclipse Kepler</a> is available as latest eclipse IDE. By default &ldquo;Target platform&rdquo; will point to latest plug-ins and features from current IDE and you will develop an RCP product based on that version of eclipse. However you can develop products based on older eclipse releases. For this you have to set &ldquo;Target Platform&rdquo; in order to include all plug-ins and features from your chosen version of eclipse.</p>

<h2>Automated build and tests</h2>

<p>You will want to automate build and tests because this can be a boring task and when humans are doing boring tasks they make mistakes. Also if you have an configuration file you can transfer build knowledge to other people as easy as sharing a file.</p>

<p>The tool suitable for build and test RCP is <a href="http://eclipse.org/tycho/" title="Tycho Project">tycho project</a> which is a set of plug-ins for <a href="http://maven.apache.org/ref/3.0/" title="Maven">maven3</a>. Tycho can have 2 approaches pom first and manifest first ( you can see some <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/11373009/should-i-use-pom-first-or-manifest-first-when-developing-osgi-application-with-m" title="Pom first vs Manifest First">pros and cons on stack-overflow</a> ). My favorite approach for RCP is manifest-first because I know from the beginning how the manifest will look like.</p>

<p>Tycho will allow you to automate:</p>

<ul>
<li>build of plug-ins</li>
<li>build of features</li>
<li>build of p2 sites</li>
<li>running of tests in an OSGi container</li>
</ul>


<h2>Automate Packaging of External dependencies</h2>

<p>The pom first approach is helpful in RCP development when you want to include some external libraries which are not OSGi. Yes you can put that dependencies in a plug-in class-path but this approach can lead to some hard to debug troubles.</p>

<p>The correct approach to this problem is to bundle your external jar of choice as an OSGi bundle. For this task you can use <a href="http://felix.apache.org/site/apache-felix-maven-bundle-plugin-bnd.html" title="Maven Bundle Plugin">maven bundle plug-in</a> and create a p2 site with all needed libraries.</p>

<p><img src="/resources/trouble-osgi-library-inclusion.png" alt="Class Cast Trouble" /></p>

<h2>Automate build of a product and further updates</h2>

<p>You can automate the assembly of your product and assembly of the p2 site. But here are some tricks. P2 support can be found in artifactory pro and nexus, but for artifactory pro you have to pay license and if you want nexus <a href="http://mrexception.blogspot.ro/2012/04/p2-support-for-nexus-oss.html" title="Nexus p2 support">here is &ldquo;how to&rdquo;</a>. If you want something simple you can configure a webdav server, with tomcat for example and use maven wagon webdav to upload the p2 generated site.</p>

<p>In the product assembly phase you specify which are your bundles and tycho will build for you products for windows, linux and macos.</p>

<h1>Tycho tutorial</h1>

<p><a href="http://codeandme.blogspot.ro/2012/12/tycho-build-1-building-plug-ins.html" title="Tycho tutorial">Here you can see a more detailed tycho tutorial</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
